So I was born
لقد ولدت ..
on the last day
في آخر يوم
of the last year of the '70s.
من آخر سنة من السبعينيات
I was raised on "Free to be you and me" --
لقد تربيت على مبدأ " كن نفسك .. فأنت حرٌ بذلك "
(cheering)
(تهليل )
hip-hop --
والهيب هوب ..
not as many woohoos for hip-hop in the house.
لا تهليل لموسيقى الهيب هوب إذا ..
Thank you. Thank you for hip-hop --
شكراً .. شكراً .. لاجل الهيب هوب
and Anita Hill.
و في عصر آنيتا هيل ..
(Cheering)
(تهليل)
My parents were radicals --
لقد كان والدي راديكاليون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
who became,
و أصبحوا لاحقاً
well, grown-ups.
ناضجين ..
My dad facetiously says,
كان والدي يقول مازحاً ..
"We wanted to save the world,
" كنا نريد أن ننقذ العالم .. ..
and instead we just got rich."
ولكننا غدونا أغنياء عوضاً عن ذلك "
We actually just got "middle class"
لقد قطنا في مناطق الطبقة المتوسطة
in Colorado Springs, Colorado,
في مدينة كالورادوا سبرينغ في ولاية كولورادوا
but you get the picture.
ويمكنكم تخيل الامر ..
I was raised with a very heavy sense
لقد نشأت بإحساس كبير
of unfinished legacy.
بذلك الارث المستمر ..
At this ripe old age of 30,
في هذه المرحلة .. مرحلة الثلاثينات
I've been thinking a lot about what it means to grow up
بت افكر .. اكثر عما يعني ان ينمو الانسان
in this horrible, beautiful time,
في تلك الفترة الرائعة\الصعبة
and I've decided, for me,
وقررت .. من أجل نفسي
it's been a real journey and paradox.
انها كانت رحلة مميزة.. تحمل مفارقات متناقضة
The first paradox
ان التناقض الاول الذي كان حينها ..
is that growing up is about rejecting the past
هو ان الاشخاص آنذاك .. كان عليهم رفض الماضي
and then promptly reclaiming it.
ومن ثم توجب عليهم محاولة استعادته
Feminism was the water I grew up in.
كانت الحركة النسوية .. المحيط الذي نشأت فيه
When I was just a little girl,
عندما كنت فتاة صغيرة
my mom started what is now
أسست والدتي
the longest-running women's film festival in the world.
ما هو الان .. اطول مهرجان افلام نسوية في العالم
So while other kids were watching sitcoms and cartoons,
فبينما كان الأطفال الآخرون حينها يشاهدون افلام الكرتون
I was watching very esoteric documentaries
كنت انا اشاهد افلام وثائقية سرية
made by and about women.
اعدت من قبل النساء .. وعن النساء
You can see how this had an influence.
ويمكنكم توقع تأثير ذلك علي
But she was not the only feminist in the house.
لم تكن والدتي مناصرة لحقوق المرأة في منزلنا فحسب
My dad actually resigned
بل كان والدي أيضاً .. فقد انسحب
from the male-only business club in my hometown
من احد نوادي الاقتصاديين الذكورية في بلدتنا
because he said he would never be part of an organization
لانه قال .. لن اكون في منظمة
that would one day welcome his son, but not his daughter.
سوف تستقبل إبني .. فحسب .. دون ابنتي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
He's actually here today.
في الحقيقة هو هنا اليوم
The trick here
الجميل في الامر ..
is my brother would become an experimental poet,
ان اخي لم يصبح رجل اعمال .. بل غدا
not a businessman,
شاعر تجريبي
but the intention was really good.
المهمة ان النية كانت سليمة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In any case, I didn't readily claim the feminist label,
على كلٍ .. انا لم اطلب ان أُسمى بمناصرة النسوية
even though it was all around me,
رغم انها كانت محيطة بي ..
because I associated it with my mom's women's groups,
لانني .. كنت اربط ذلك المسمى .. بوالدتي وصديقاتها ..
her swishy skirts and her shoulder pads --
اللاتي يرتدين التنانير المقصفة .. والملابس ذوات حاملات الكتف
none of which had much cachet
والتي لم تكن اي منها تثير اهتمامي
in the hallways of Palmer High School
خاصة لانني طالبة في ثانوية تلال بالمير
where I was trying to be cool at the time.
حيث كنت احاول ان اكون عصرية آنذاك
But I suspected there was something really important
وكنت اشك بوجود فائدة ما ولا بد من
about this whole feminism thing,
الحركة النسوية ككل
so I started covertly tiptoeing into my mom's bookshelves
لذا بدأت اتلصص على رف كتب والدتي ..
and picking books off and reading them --
واختار كتباً وابدأ بقراءتها
never, of course, admitting that I was doing so.
دون أن أخبر احداً بذلك ..
I didn't actually claim the feminist label
في الحقيقة لم اعلن الانتساب الى الحركة النسوية ..
until I went to Barnard College
حتى انضمامي الى كلية برنارد
and I heard Amy Richards and Jennifer Baumgardner speak for the first time.
فسمعت حينها " آمي ريتشاردز .. و جينفر بامجرادنير " تتحدثان للمرة الاولى
They were the co-authors of a book called "Manifesta."
انهما مؤلفتا كتاب " مانيفيستنا "
So what very profound epiphany, you might ask,
ربما سوف تتسائلون مالذي جعلني في النهاية
was responsible for my feminist click moment?
اقرر الانضمام الى الحركة النسوية
Fishnet stockings.
انها جوارب شبكة صيد السمك
Jennifer Baumgardner was wearing them.
التي كانت " جينفر بامجرادنير " ترتديهم
I thought they were really hot.
لقد رأيت انها مثيرةٌ حقاً
I decided, okay, I can claim the feminist label.
فقررت في النهاية ان انتمي للحركة النسوية
Now I tell you this --
انا اخبركم بهذا ..
I tell you this at the risk of embarrassing myself,
انا اخبركم بهذا .. وانا اخاطر بأن احرج نفسي .
because I think part of the work of feminism
وذلك لأن الحركة النسوية جزء منها
is to admit that aesthetics, that beauty,
قائم على الاعتراف بالجماليات .. بالرونق
that fun do matter.
ان المتعة .. مهمة ..
There are lots of very modern political movements
هناك الكثير من الحركات السياسية الحديثة ..
that have caught fire in no small part
قد تهمشت لانها لم تتواكب
because of cultural hipness.
مع الفكر الثقافي
Anyone heard of these two guys as an example?
هل سمع أحدكم بهؤلاء الاثنين ؟
So my feminism is very indebted to my mom's,
ان انتمائي للحركة النسوية يختلف عن إنتماء والدتي ..
but it looks very different.
انه يبدو مختلفاً ..
My mom says, "patriarchy."
والدتي تقول " المجتمع ذكوري متلسط "
I say, "intersectionality."
انا اقول " المجتمع متقاطع "
So race, class, gender, ability,
ان الجنس .. المنزلة .. العرق .. الانجاز .. الفرص
all of these things go into our experiences
كلها امور تدور حولها خبراتنا ..
of what it means to be a woman.
فيما يخص كوننا إناثاً
Pay equity? Yes. Absolutely a feminist issue.
الاجور المتساوية .. نعم انها حتماً قضية نسوية
But for me, so is immigration. (Applause)
ولكن بالنسبة لي .. الهجرة هي كذلك أيضاَ
Thank you.
شكراً
My mom says, "Protest march."
والدتي تقول .. لنحل ذلك بمسيرة اعتراض
I say, "Online organizing."
انا اقول لنحل ذلك .. بالتنظيم الانترنتي
I co-edit, along with a collective
استطعت مع زملائي
of other super-smart, amazing women,
وهن إناث شديدات الذكاء ..
a site called Feministing.com.
تأسيس موقع اسمه " Feministing.com "
We are the most widely read feminist publication ever,
نحن الناشر الاكثر قراءة على الاطلاق فيما يخص القضايا النسوية
and I tell you this
وانا اخبركم هذا
because I think it's really important to see
لانني اريدكم ان تروا اهمية
that there's a continuum.
الاستمرار
Feminist blogging is basically the 21st century version
في التدوين النسوي في القرن الحادي والعشرين
of consciousness raising.
من اجل زيادة الوعي العام بالقضايا النسوية
But we also have a straightforward political impact.
لقد استطعنا ان نحقق مكاسب سياسية ..
Feministing has been able
لقد استطاعت الحركة النسوية
to get merchandise pulled off the shelves of Walmart.
ان تسحب بعض المنتجات المهينة للمرأة من على رفوف متاجر " وال مارت "
We got a misogynist administrator sending us hate-mail
لقد استطعنا ان نعزل عن العمل مدراء
fired from a Big Ten school.
عنصرين تجاه المرأة من 10 مدارس
And one of our biggest successes
واحد اكبر انجازاتنا
is we get mail from teenage girls in the middle of Iowa
التي نفتخر بها .. هو انه وصلتنا رسائل الكترونية من وسط ولاية آيوا
who say, "I Googled Jessica Simpson and stumbled on your site.
من فتيات مراهقات يقلن " كنا نبحث عن جيسكا سمبسون على الانترنت .. فاعترضنا موقعكم ..
I realized feminism wasn't about man-hating and Birkenstocks."
لقد اكتشفنا ان الحركات النسوية .. ليست مناهضة للرجل .. او انها معادية له ... بفضلكم "
So we're able to pull in the next generation
نحن قادرون على جذب الجيل الجديد
in a totally new way.
بطريقة جديدة تماماً
My mom says, "Gloria Steinem."
والدتي تقول " جلوريا ستينيم " هي المثال
I say, "Samhita Mukhopadhyay,
انا اقول " سماهيتا موخوبادهياي ..
Miriam Perez, Ann Friedman,
مريم بيريز .. آن فيردمان ..
Jessica Valenti, Vanessa Valenti,
جيسيكا فالينتي .. فينيسا فالينتي ..
and on and on and on and on."
والكثير الكثير منهن .. "
We don't want one hero.
نحن لا نريد بطلة واحدة فحسب ..
We don't want one icon.
نحن لا نريد رمزاً واحداً فحسب ..
We don't want one face.
لا نريد وجهاً واحداً
We are thousands of women and men across this country
نحن آلاف من الرجال والنساء من جميع انحاء هذا الوطن
doing online writing, community organizing,
نقول بالكتابة الالكترونية .. والتنظيم المجتمعي
changing institutions from the inside out --
وتغير المنظمات .. من الداخل
all continuing the incredible work
والخارج .. لكي نكمل العمل الرائع
that our mothers and grandmothers started.
الذي بدأته أمهاتنا .. وجداتنا
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Which brings me to the second paradox:
مما يوصلنا الى التناقض الثاني
sobering up about our smallness
التنبه عن صغر حجمنا
and maintaining faith in our greatness
والحفاظ على الايمان في عظمتنا
all at once.
في آن واحد
Many in my generation --
العديد من بنات جيلي
because of well-intentioned parenting and self-esteem education --
وبسبب التربية ذات النية الطيبة .. والتعليم ذا المنحى الواحد ..
were socialized to believe
يتم تربيتنا ..
that we were special little snowflakes --
بأننا رقائق ثلج بلورية صغيرة ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
who were going to go out and save the world.
والتي سوف تنقذ العالم
These are three words many of us were raised with.
هذه كلمات نشأت الكثير من الاناث عليها
We walk across graduation stages,
نحن ننمو خلال المراحل التعليمية ..
high on our overblown expectations,
ومن ثم نرفع من توقعاتنا الخيالية ..
and when we float back down to earth,
وما ان نطال الواقع .. حتى نعود الى الارض ..
we realize we don't know what the heck it means
ندرك ان تلك الكلمات لا تعني اي شيء ..ولانعي
to actually save the world anyway.
كيفية انقاذ العالم ..
The mainstream media often paints my generation
ان الاعلام بصورة عامة
as apathetic,
يحاول ان يظهر جيلنا وكأنه غير مبال
and I think it's much more accurate
واعتقد ان من الدقة
to say we are deeply overwhelmed.
ان يتم وصفه انه " مفعهم - مثقل "
And there's a lot to be overwhelmed about, to be fair --
وهناك الكثير من الامور التي تثقل كاهله ..
an environmental crisis,
مثل الازمة البيئية
wealth disparity in this country
توزيع الثروات في هذا البلد
unlike we've seen since 1928,
ليس كما كان في عام 1928 .. وذلك في ..
and globally,
العالم كله ..
a totally immoral and ongoing wealth disparity.
ان التوزيع الحالي غير عادل .. واستقطابي جداً ..
Xenophobia's on the rise. The trafficking of women and girls.
ناهيكم عن مشاكل " رهاب الاجانب " والاتجار بالنساء والفتيات
It's enough to make you feel very overwhelmed.
ان هذه المشاكل بذاتها كافية لتُثقل كاهل هذا الجيل
I experienced this firsthand myself
لقد كنت مندفعة جداً
when I graduated from Barnard College in 2002.
عندما تخرجت في عام 2002 من كلية بارنارد
I was fired up; I was ready to make a difference.
كنت مشتعلة .. كنت اريد ان احدث تغيراً
I went out and I worked at a non-profit,
عملت لمنظمات لا ربحية ..
I went to grad school, I phone-banked,
ذهبت بزيارات الى المدارس الثانوية .. قمت بحملات توعية على الهاتف
I protested, I volunteered,
تظاهرت .. تطوعت
and none of it seemed to matter.
ولم يبدو ان اياً من ذلك يجدي نفعاً
And on a particularly dark night
في احدى الليالي الصعاب على نفسي
of December of 2004,
من ديسمبر 2004
I sat down with my family,
جلست الى عائلتي
and I said that I had become very disillusioned.
وقلت لهم لقد بدأت اصاب بالهوس ..
I admitted that I'd actually had a fantasy -- kind of a dark fantasy --
كان لدي حلم كبير .. اصبح لدي كابوس اسود ..
of writing a letter
انا اتخيل انني سوف اكتب رسالة
about everything that was wrong with the world
فيها كل شيء سيء في هذا العالم
and then lighting myself on fire
ومن ثم احرق نفسي
on the White House steps.
امام عتبات البيت الابيض
My mom
قالت لي والدتي
took a drink of her signature Sea Breeze,
بعد ان ارتشفت من كأس عصيرها الاستوائي
her eyes really welled with tears,
واعينها مغمورة بالدمع ..
and she looked right at me and she said,
بعد ان نظرت مباشرة الي ..
"I will not stand
لن اقف .. واشاهدك
for your desperation."
تقعين في احباطك
She said, "You are smarter, more creative
انت اذكى .. أوعى ..
and more resilient than that."
واكثر واقعية من هذا الامر "
Which brings me to my third paradox.
مما يوصلني الى التناقض الثالث ..
Growing up is about aiming to succeed wildly
وهو " أن تنمو وكلك أمل بنجاح باهر ..
and being fulfilled by failing really well.
رغم انك محاط بفشل شنيع من حولك "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There's a writer I've been deeply influenced by, Parker Palmer,
هناك كاتب تأثرت به كثيراً .. انه باركير بالمير
and he writes that many of us are often whiplashed
وهو يكتب عادة ما يدور في خلدنا ..
"between arrogant overestimation of ourselves
بين غرورنا المتعنت ..
and a servile underestimation of ourselves."
وبين إحباطنا المستشري "
You may have guessed by now,
يمكنكم ان تروا ..
I did not light myself on fire.
انني لم اشعل نفسي ..
I did what I know to do in desperation, which is write.
لقد قمت بما كنت آراه حلاً للإحباط .. لقد خلدت الى الكتابة
I wrote the book I needed to read.
كتبت كتاباً .. كنت احتاج ان أقرأه ..
I wrote a book about eight incredible people
كتبت كتاباً عن 8 اشخاص مميزين
all over this country
في هذا الوطن
doing social justice work.
يقومون بعمل من اجل العدالة الاجتماعية
I wrote about Nia Martin-Robinson,
كتبت عن " نيا مارتين روبنسون "
the daughter of Detroit and two civil rights activists,
ابن ولاية ديترويت .. وكتبت عن اثنين من مناصري حقوق الانسان
who's dedicating her life
وكتبت عن من سخر حياته
to environmental justice.
من اجل العدالة البيئية
I wrote about Emily Apt
وكتبت عن إيميلي آبت
who initially became a caseworker in the welfare system
والتي غدت صاحبة قضية في نظام الرعاية الاجتماعية
because she decided that was the most noble thing she could do,
لانها ادركت ان هذا أنبل شيء يمكن للفرد ان يقوم به .
but quickly learned, not only did she not like it,
ولكنها ادركت على الفور .. انها في المكان
but she wasn't really good at it.
الغير ملائم لها ..
Instead, what she really wanted to do was make films.
وبدلا من هذا .. خلدت الى صناعة الافلام ..
So she made a film about the welfare system
قامت بانتاج فلم عن نظام الرعاية الصحية
and had a huge impact.
وكان له أثرٌ بالغٌ جداً
I wrote about Maricela Guzman, the daughter of Mexican immigrants,
وكتبت عن مارسيلا جوزمان .. التي تنتمي الى المهاجرين المكسيكين
who joined the military so she could afford college.
الذين ينضمون الى صفوف الجيش .. لكي يستطيعوا ان يوفروا مصاريف دراستهم الجامعية
She was actually sexually assaulted in boot camp
ولقد تم الاعتداء جنسيا عليها في احدى الثكنات
and went on to co-organize a group
ومن ثم ساهمت بتنظيم مجموعة
called the Service Women's Action Network.
تدعى " شبكة نساء الجيش الفعالة "
What I learned from these people and others
وقد تعلمت من هؤلاء الاشخاص ومن غيرهم ..
was that I couldn't judge them
انني لا استطيع ان احكم على الفرد
based on their failure to meet their very lofty goals.
بناءاً على فشله في تحقيق اهدافه الكبيرة جداً ..
Many of them are working in deeply intractable systems --
فالعديد منهم يعملون في انظمة معقدة جداً
the military, congress,
مثل الجيش .. والكونغرس
the education system, etc.
والنظام التعليمي ..
But what they managed to do within those systems
ولكان ما استطاع هؤلاء القيام به في هذه الانظمة
was be a humanizing force.
هو ان يصبحوا " قوة إنسانية "
And at the end of the day,
وفي نهاية الامر . يقاس النجاح . ..
what could possibly be more important than that?
بالقول المهم جداً
Cornel West says, "Of course it's a failure.
المنقول عن " كونيل ويست " .. " نعم انه فشل ..
But how good a failure is it?"
ولكن أي فشل رائع هو هذا ؟ "
This isn't to say we give up our wildest, biggest dreams.
ان هذا لا يعني ان تتخلى عن احلامك الكبيرة ..
It's to say we operate on two levels.
انه يعني ان تعمل عليها على منحيين ..
On one,
الاول
we really go after changing these broken systems
ان نحسن قدر المستطاع في تلك الانظمة المختلة ..
of which we find ourselves a part.
التي نجد انفسنا فيها ..
But on the other, we root our self-esteem
والثاني ان نقيم أنفسنا .. تبعاً لانجازاتنا اليومية
in the daily acts of trying to make one person's day
كان نحسن من يوم فرد واحد على الاقل .
more kind, more just, etc.
بان نصبح كريمين اكثر .. لطفاء اكثر .. ان نقدم أكثر !
So when I was a little girl,
عندما كنت طفلة صغيرة
I had a couple of very strange habits.
كان لدي عادات غريبة
One of them was
كانت واحدة منها
I used to lie on the kitchen floor of my childhood home,
اننا كنت استلقي على ارضية المطبخ في صغري
and I would suck the thumb of my left hand
وكنت امتص ابهام يدي اليسرى
and hold my mom's cold toes with my right hand.
وامسك بإصبع قدم والدتي بيدي اليمنى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was listening to her talk on the phone, which she did a lot.
كنت احاول التنصت عليها اثناء استماعها الى الهاتف .. والتي كانت تستخدمه كثيراً ..
She was talking about board meetings,
وهي تتحدث عن التنظيم .. والمؤتمرات
she was founding peace organizations,
وهي تؤسس للحملات السلمية
she was coordinating carpools, she was consoling friends --
وهي تنظم المسيرات .. وهي تستشير الاصدقاء
all these daily acts of care and creativity.
كل هذه الانشطة اليومية التي تحمل الاهتمام والابداع
And surely, at three and four years old,
في الثالثة والرابعة من عمري
I was listening to the soothing sound of her voice,
كنت استمتع بصوتها الهادىء ..
but I think I was also getting my first lesson in activist work.
ولكني كنت في نفس الاثناء اتعلم درسي الاول في النشاط الاجتماعي
The activists I interviewed
ان النشطاء الذين قابلت
had nothing in common, literally, except for one thing,
لا يملكون اي شيء مشترك فيما بينهما .. باستثناء شيء واحد ..
which was that they all cited their mothers
وهو .. انهم كنَّ يُشرنَّ الى ان امهاتهن
as their most looming and important
هن ذوات التأثير الاكبر والاهم
activist influences.
في نشاطهم الاجتماعي
So often, particularly at a young age,
لذا .. وتحديداً في الاوقات اليافعة من عمرنا ..
we look far afield
جميعناً يبحث في الافق
for our models of the meaningful life,
عن النماذج المعتبرة في حياته لكي يقتدي بها .. ويعطي لحياته معنى ..
and sometimes they're in our own kitchens,
لكن احيانا تكمن تلك " القدوة " في مطبخ منزلنا !
talking on the phone, making us dinner,
تتحدث على الهاتف .. تُعد العشاء
doing all that keeps the world going around and around.
تقوم بكل ما يجعل العالم يمضي قدماً .. في مسيرته
My mom and so many women like her
ان والدتي .. كما الكثير من النسوة حول العالم
have taught me that life is not about glory,
علموني ان الحياة ليست عن المجد والشهرة ..
or certainty, or security even.
او اليقين .. او الأمن حتى ..
It's about embracing the paradox.
انها عن تقدير التناقضات ..
It's about acting in the face of overwhelm.
انها عن مجابهة الثقل الكبير الذي يعتري الفرد في حياته دون تململ
And it's about loving people really well.
انها عن حب الاشخاص من حولنا بشدة
And at the end of the day,
ففي نهاية اليوم ..
these things make for a lifetime
هذه الامور هي التي تجعل حياتنا .. حياة رائعة مميزة
of challenge and reward.
هي التي تعطي معنى التحدي .. ومعنى الانجاز
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)